In this video we will cover heap level 0 from exploit-exercises.com/protostar.
在这段视频中，我们将从exploit-exercises.com/protostar中介绍堆级别0。
It’s the heap exploitation introductory challenge and is very easy.
这是堆利用的入门挑战，非常简单。
We again compile this on a Ubuntu 16.04 LTS version, so basically a modern system, to
我们再次在Ubuntu16.04LTS版本上编译它，所以基本上是一个现代系统，
see if or how it’s still exploitable.
看看它是否还是可以被利用的或者如何被利用的。
And spoiler alert, nothing changed for this challenge, it’s super straight forward.
剧透警报，这项挑战没有改变，它是超直向前。
But I have a special idea for this video and even if it’s a bit easy for you, you might
但我对这个视频有一个特别的想法，即使对你来说有点简单，你也可以
want to checkout what else we learn at the end.
想看看最后我们还学到了什么。
In the previous videos of this series I usually create the exploit and then think of a way
在本系列之前的视频中，我通常会创建漏洞，然后思考一种方法
how to explain and show it to you.
如何向你解释和展示。
But this is so simple, that I thought it would be cool if I would instead record myself solving
但这太简单了，我想如果我把自己的解决方法记录下来会很酷的。
it, kind of like a blind solve or a speedrun.
它有点像盲解或快跑。
But I didn’t try to be super fast but it was quite straight forward and I include all
但我没有试着超快，但它是相当直接的，我包括所有
the mistakes and pauses I made.
我犯的错误和停顿。
And now we will step through the video and I explain to you what I have been thinking
现在我们来看看视频，我向你解释一下我的想法
in different moments and point out some other things.
在不同的时刻，指出一些其他的事情。
In the top right corner you can also see a timer that will keep track of how long it
在右上角，您还可以看到一个计时器，它将跟踪多长时间
took me in real time.
实时带我去。
But before we start doing the exploit let’s have a look at the code again.
但是在我们开始利用这个漏洞之前，让我们再看看代码。
There are two functions winner() and nowinner().
有两个函数winner() 和nowinner() 。
And obviously we have to somehow call winner().
显然，我们必须以某种方式称之为winner() 。
We can also see there are two structs that get space allocated for them on the heap.
我们还可以看到有两个结构在堆上为它们分配了空间。
And this fp construct here looks complex, but you can ignore that weirdness because
这里的fp构造看起来很复杂，但是你可以忽略这种奇怪，因为
when you look in the code it’s clear what it does.
当您查看代码时，很清楚它是做什么的。
We set fp to nowinner.
我们将fp设置为nowinner。
Notice how nowinner has no parantheses, this means it’s not being called.
注意到现在的内在没有偏执，这意味着它没有被召唤。
This is literally the function pointer and adding paraentheses would cause a call.
这实际上是函数指针，添加parenthese将导致调用。
And then later we have those paraentheses for fp.
然后，我们有了FP的副焓。
And fp has been set to point to nowinner, so nowinner is executed().
并且fp被设置为指向nowinner，所以nowinner被执行() 。
And our goal is it to somehow use the strcpy, which will overflow the name buffer which
我们的目标是以某种方式使用strcpy，它将溢出名称缓冲区
is only 64byte large and overwrite the function pointer.
只有64字节大并覆盖函数指针。
So sounds easy.
听起来很简单。
I start by opening up the binary in gdb.
我首先打开gdb中的二进制文件。
And do a first test execution, but I run into a segfault which startled me for a few seconds,
做第一次测试，但是我遇到了一个segfault，它让我吃惊了几秒钟，
but then I realized I forgot the argument parameter again.
但后来我意识到我又忘记了参数。
The strcpy uses the first argument to copy into name.
strcpy使用第一个参数复制到name中。
Ok now we had a clean execution.
好吧，现在我们干净利落地处决了。
Now I want to set a good breakpoint so I disassemble main.
现在我想设置一个好的断点，这样我就可以分解main了。
I’m quickly scanning the assembler code here, mainly looking at the different function
我在这里快速扫描汇编程序代码，主要是查看不同的函数
calls to figure out what corresponds to what in the C code.
调用以找出与C代码中的内容对应的内容。
And at first I was thinking about setting a breakpoint before or after the strcpy, to
起初我想在strcpy之前或之后设置一个断点，
catch the before and after of the overflow, but in the last moment then figured that I
抓住溢出的前后，但在最后一刻，我发现
probably don’t need to look at it this closely, and I can simply go to the magic position
可能不需要仔细观察，我可以直接进入魔法状态
right away.
马上。
The call rdx.
呼叫RDX。
This is calling the function pointer that contains nowinner().
这将调用包含nowinner() 的函数指针。
Ok, so I execute it again and we hit the breakpoint.
好的，所以我再次执行它，我们到达了断点。
Now this challenge is about a heap overflow, so I first check the virtual memory map of
现在这个挑战是关于堆溢出的，所以我首先检查
the process with vmmap.
使用vmmap的进程。
Here you can see in which memory regions we have the binary itself with the code and data
在这里，您可以看到哪些内存区域中有二进制代码和数据
segments, we can also see where the stack is and where shared libraries like libc are
段，我们还可以看到堆栈在哪里，以及像libc这样的共享库在哪里。
loaded too, and we also have the heap here.
也加载了，这里还有堆。
So obviously I want to check out how the heap looks like.
所以很明显我想看看堆的样子。
Examine 32 64bit hex values from the start of the heap.
从堆的开头检查32个64位十六进制值。
I immediately look for the name we entered as an argument, which was “AAAA”, so here
我立即查找我们作为参数输入的名称，它是“aaaa”，所以这里
they are.
他们是。
And I also immediately look for the function pointer.
我也会立即查找函数指针。
This looks like an address.
这像是地址。
Quick sanity check with the disassemble command.
使用disassemble命令快速进行健全性检查。
Here is a puts call using this address as a paremter, and so that is our nowinner string.
这里是一个使用这个地址作为paremter的puts调用，所以这就是我们现在的内部字符串。
So yep, that’s nowinner.
所以是的，这就是现在的内在。
So now we want to overwrite that with winner, so we need that address.
所以现在我们想用winner覆盖它，所以我们需要那个地址。
Here it is.
在这里。
Next I need to figure out how much we have to overflow, to do that I simply look at the
接下来，我需要弄清楚我们需要溢出多少，为了实现这一点，我只需看看
addresses to the left.
地址在左边。
Address of the start of the name ends in 0x10, and the function pointer is ath 0x60.
名称开头的地址以0x10结尾，函数指针为ATH 0x60。
So we have an offset of 0x50.
所以我们有一个0x50的偏移量。
So now I’m feeling confident and actually drop out of gdb and hope to have a working
所以现在我很自信，实际上退出了gdb，希望能有个工作。
exploit right away.
立即利用。
So I start by writing a short python inline script to print the exploit string.
因此，我首先编写一个简短的python内联脚本来打印漏洞字符串。
Essentially we need a couple of characters as padding to reach the function pointer and
实际上，我们需要几个字符作为填充来到达函数指针和
so I print a few As.
所以我打印了一些。
Quick check again how many that was, 0x60-0x10 so we need 0x50.
再次快速检查有多少个，0x60-0x10，所以我们需要0x50。
After that we need the address of winner.
之后我们需要获胜者的地址。
So 0x40, OOPS!
所以0x40，哎呀！
Almost made a mistake - this stil happens to me sometime, we obviously have to start
几乎犯了一个错误-这个问题有时会发生在我身上，显然我们必须开始
with 0xf6, 0x05 and then 0x40.
使用0xF6、0x05，然后是0x40。
Because of the endianess.
因为有大麻。
Now for a sanity and debugging step I pipe that output into hexdump to see if it is what
现在，对于一个健全的和调试步骤，我将输出管道导入hexdump，看看它是否是
I expect.
我期待。
But then I notice a 0x0a at the end, and that’s a newline.
但是我注意到末尾有一个0x0A，这是一个换行符。
Python print will add a newline at the end which we don’t want.
python print将在末尾添加一个我们不需要的换行符。
So now I change the script to use the sys module instead in order to directly write
因此，现在我将脚本改为使用sys模块来直接写入
a string to stdout, so we don’t have a newline.
一个字符串到stdout，所以我们没有换行符。
And I verify that again with hexdump.
我再次用hexdump验证这一点。
And then I’m basically done and try it on the target binary.
然后我基本上完成了，在目标二进制文件上进行尝试。
So the input is passed as argument, so I use backticks to execute the inner python command,
所以输入作为参数传递，所以我使用反勾号来执行内部python命令，
and the output is then basically replaced by it and placed here as the arguments.
然后输出基本上被它替换，放在这里作为参数。
Level passed!
平地通过！
Awesome!
令人惊叹的！
I executed the winner function().
我执行了winner函数() 。
You see this was super simple.
你看这太简单了。
So when I was writing this script with the commentary of my recording, I noticed a small
所以当我用录音带上的解说词写这个剧本时，我注意到
detail that I didn’t think about.
我没想到的细节。
And I actually never thought about before.
实际上我以前从来没有想过。
So here is the heap output again.
这里是堆输出。
Do you see this data down here?
你看到下面的数据了吗？
That is clearly ascii.
这显然是ASCII码。
And that’s weird, in our program we did not allocate any string like this on the heap.
这很奇怪，在我们的程序中，我们没有在堆中分配这样的字符串。
So how did this happen?
这是怎么发生的？
When you look at this ascii text, then you will realize it’s in fact the printf output.
当您查看这个ASCII文本时，您会发现它实际上是printf输出。
But why is that on the heap?
但为什么会这样？
Let’s investigate.
让我们调查一下。
First I thought we could checkout valgrind.
首先，我想我们可以去看看瓦尔格林。
Valgrind is an instrumentation framework for building dynamic analysis tools.
Valgrind是用于构建动态分析工具的仪器框架。
There are Valgrind tools that can automatically detect many memory management and threading
Valgrind工具可以自动检测许多内存管理和线程
bugs, and profile your programs in detail.
错误，并详细介绍您的程序。
I really should use valgrind more often, I use it wayy to little.
我真的应该更经常地使用Valgrind，我经常使用它。
But here is for example the valgrind output with tracing mallocs enabled.
但下面是启用跟踪mallocs的valgrind输出。
And then we run our heap0 level.
然后我们运行heap0级别。
And we can indeed see here our two mallocs of the structs we do, but also a malloc we
我们在这里可以看到我们所做的结构的两个malloc，也可以看到malloc
didn’t do of 1024.
不是1024年的事。
That’s also the only memory that is freed again.
这也是唯一被释放的内存。
The mallocs we do have no free.
我们没有自由的马洛克人。
So why is that happening?
为什么会这样？
Another interesting output is strace.
另一个有趣的输出是strace。
Strace traces syscalls.
strace跟踪系统调用。
And while we don’t see mallocs here, because malloc is just some algorithm and memory managment
虽然我们在这里看不到malloc，因为malloc只是一些算法和内存管理。
implemented in libc, we can see the brk syscall, which gets the memory from the operating system
在libc中实现，我们可以看到brk syscall，它从操作系统获取内存。
in the first place.
首先。
So this is where we get memory that will then be used by libc for the heap.
所以这就是我们得到内存的地方，然后libc将使用它来处理堆。
So if malloc is a libc function, we can also checkout ltrace, which traces linked dynamic
所以如果malloc是libc函数，我们也可以检查ltrace，它跟踪链接的动态
library function calls.
库函数调用。
But oddly enough we only see two mallocs for the two structs.
但奇怪的是，我们只看到两个结构的两个malloc。
Nothing about the mysterious third malloc.
关于神秘的第三个malloc什么都没有。
It might not be immediately obvious, but that is actually already a really good hint that
这可能不是很明显，但实际上已经是一个很好的提示
the mysterious malloc did not happen from a dynamically linked library call.
神秘的malloc不是从动态链接的库调用中发生的。
Which means, this malloc must have been executed for example by libc itself.
也就是说，这个malloc必须由libc本身执行。
And valgrind is a bit smarter and also traces these internal mallocs.
Valgrind有点聪明，还可以追踪到这些内部的malloc。
For the third test I create a simple program that calls puts, so it prints a string.
对于第三个测试，我创建了一个调用puts的简单程序，因此它打印一个字符串。
Because we know the heap did contain the printf output so it must have to do something with
因为我们知道堆确实包含printf输出，所以它必须对
that.
那。
And then we can debug that program and set a breakpoint on brk.
然后我们可以调试这个程序并在BRK上设置一个断点。
Remember brk is the syscall that is called when a program requests additional virtual
记住，brk是当程序请求其他虚拟机时调用的系统调用
memory, and so this is called when the heap is set up.
内存，所以在设置堆时调用它。
And the heap is not always setup, only if it is required.
并且堆并不总是设置的，只有在需要时才设置。
So if we assume printf or puts calls malloc, it would have to setup the heap first.
因此，如果我们假设printf或puts调用malloc，它必须首先设置堆。
Now that’s also why I created this small test program, because the original heap0 has
这也是我创建这个小测试程序的原因，因为原来的heap0
obviously regular mallocs before the printf, which makes it a bit annoying, so this is
显然，打印前有规则的malloc，这让它有点烦人，所以这是
a clean example.
一个干净的例子。
On a second note, when you set a breakpoint with a symbol name like brk, there has to
第二个注意事项是，当您使用BRK这样的符号名设置断点时，必须
be a symbol name for it.
成为它的符号名。
And a syscall doesn’t have a symbol name.
系统调用没有符号名。
A syscall is an asembler interrup instruction with a number as paramter to indicate which
系统调用是一个以数字作为参数来指示
syscall you want.
您需要的系统调用。
But there is a brk symbol, but it’s not initially found.
但是有一个BRK符号，但最初没有找到。
You first have to execute the program in order to load the dynamic library libc, which does
首先必须执行该程序才能加载动态库libc，这是
contain a brk symbol.
包含BRK符号。
And infact that is a regular function as a wrapper around the brk syscall.
实际上，它是一个常规函数，作为BRK系统调用的包装器。
So anything inside of libc would not directly do the syscall interrupt, it would call the
所以libc中的任何内容都不会直接执行syscall中断，它会调用
internal brk function.
内部BRK功能。
So that;s why we can easily set a breakpoint like this.
所以我们可以很容易地设置这样的断点。
Long story short we can now continue and hit that breakpoint and then examine the function
长话短说，我们现在可以继续并点击该断点，然后检查函数
backtrace which tells us which functions have been called that lead to this brk call.
backtrace，它告诉我们哪些函数被调用，导致了这个brk调用。
I clean that up a bit.
我会清理一下。
So here we go.
我们走吧。
And as you can see it starts with IO_puts.
正如你所看到的，它从输入输出开始。
You can also look at the libc code for that stuff, I just pulled up some mirror of libc
你也可以看看这些东西的libc代码，我刚刚打开了libc的镜子
on github, and you can read the code there.
在Github上，您可以在那里读取代码。
The reason why the function is not called puts, but IO_puts, eventhough we only use
为什么函数不被称为puts，但io_puts，eventhough we only use
puts when we call it, has to do with a lot of C macros in libc.
当我们调用它时，它与libc中的许多c宏有关。
I find it really difficult to read that code.
我发现读这段代码真的很困难。
For example we know that the next function has the symbol name _IO_new_file_xsputn, but
例如，我们知道下一个函数的符号名为“IO”new“file”xsputn，但是
that doesn’t show up in the C code.
这不会出现在C代码中。
But there is this similarely called IO_sputn, which when you look that up leads to a macro
但是有一个类似的叫做io_sputn，当你往上看的时候，它会导致一个宏
that says that it’s actually IO_Xsputn.
也就是说它实际上是IO输入。
Which itself is another macro that is JUMP2 with __xsputn as the first argument , and
它本身是另一个以xputn作为第一个参数的jump2宏，并且
JUMP2 is obviously another macro.
Jump2显然是另一个宏。
And it just keeps going like that.
就这样继续下去。
Feel free to do that on your own.
你可以自己做。
But if we trust our trace we can see that at some point it calls doallocbuffer.
但是，如果我们相信我们的追踪，我们可以在某个时刻看到它称之为DoallocBuffer。
And there is also a comment saying: “Allocate a buffer if needed”.
还有一条评论说：“如果需要，分配一个缓冲区”。
So this 1024 byte malloc has to do with the standard output buffer.
所以这个1024字节的malloc与标准输出缓冲区有关。
A printf doesn’t immediatly result in a syscall write, but libc implements a lot of
printf不会立即导致系统调用写入，但是libc实现了很多
stuff like this in order to achieve higher performances by buffering output instead of
像这样的东西，为了获得更高的性能，通过缓冲输出而不是
waiting for files, or writing a few bigger chunks instead of a lot of small pieces.
等待文件，或者写一些更大的块而不是很多小的块。
Yeah.
是啊。
I would consider this a solved mystery.
我认为这是一个已解开的谜。
Just a little excursion into the inner workings of programs.
仅仅是对程序内部工作的一点探索。
I hope you liked that.
希望你喜欢。
See you next week.
下周见。